Guide to the Russell Lee Collection
The Wittliff Collections
Russell Lee Collection
1881-1992
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Lee, Russell, 1903-1986
SWWC.SWMP 001
21 boxes
18 Linear Feet
This collection of photographs, correspondence, personal and legal documents, artifacts, paintings, and publications ranges in date from 1881-1992 (bulk dates 1936-1965). It has been arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Personal Documents; III. Legal Documents; IV. President's Commission on Coal; V. Exhibits and Publications; VI. Interviews; VII. Clippings; VIII. Awards and Artifacts; IX. Photographs of Russell and Jean Lee; X. Photographs by Russell Lee; XI. Paintings by Russell Lee; and XII. Camera Equipment
Scope and Contents
This collection of photographs, correspondence, personal and legal documents, artifacts, paintings, and publications ranges in date from 1881-1992 (bulk dates 1936-1965). It has been arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Personal Documents; III. Legal Documents; IV. President's Commission on Coal; V. Exhibits and Publications; VI. Interviews; VII. Clippings; VIII. Awards and Artifacts; IX. Photographs of Russell and Jean Lee; X. Photographs by Russell Lee; XI. Paintings by Russell Lee; and XII. Camera Equipment
Letters from Jack Hurley to Russell Lee, regarding Hurley's book, Russell Lee: Photographer, comprise the bulk of the correspondence series. Three of Russell Lee's FSA field notebooks, which were used to write captions for his FSA photographs, are located in the Personal Documents series. Other personal documents include Lee's mother's diary (1900-1901), the family Bible, and several of Jean Lee's writing assignments (1967). Legal documents include divorce and marriage records, passports, and Lee's grandmother's will. Of particular note are paintings by Lee which pre-date his interest in photography, and three of Lee's cameras, along with their accessories, such as a hand held flash and various viewfinders.
The seventy-eight photographs of Lee, dating from his childhood through his early eighties, were taken by unknown photographers and by well known photographers, such as Ave Bonar. Some are portraits, many are candid photographs.
The three-hundred fifty-two photographs in this collection taken by Lee provide an overview of his entire career. The bulk of the professional photographs taken by Lee include work from his years with the Farm Security Administration (FSA), from 1936 to 1942. One hundred and thirty of the FSA prints are rare, vintage prints. Other photographs include those taken while he was serving with the Air Transport Command (ATC) from 1942 through 1945, and documentary work undertaken for the Coal Mines Administration in 1946, arranged in chronological order.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Jean Lee and Bill & Sally Wittliff beginning in 1986.
Related Materials
The Wittliff Collections also holds a collection of Jean Lee material (SWMP Collection 002).
Also of note is "Retracing Russell Lee" Project Collection (Collection 052).
Biographical Notes
Russell Lee was born on July 21, 1903, in Ottawa, Illinois. His parents' divorce, the death of his mother, and supervision by three successive guardians created an unsettled childhood for Lee. In 1917 he was sent to Culver Military Academy (CMA), which provided some stability in his life. He attended CMA until 1921, then enrolled at Lehigh University, in Pennsylvania. He graduated in 1925 with a degree in chemical engineering and joined the Certainteed Products Company in Marseilles, Illinois.
In 1927 he married painter Doris Emrick. The following year, Lee was transferred to Kansas City, where he became so bored with his job he resigned to pursue painting. After moving to San Francisco in 1929, the Lees resettled a year later in an artists colony in Woodstock, New York. Lee subsequently became increasingly frustrated with his limitations as a painter. In 1935, at the suggestion of a friend, he bought his first camera and his enthusiasm for photography quickly grew. He explored the technical aspects of the craft, experimenting with developing chemicals, exposure speeds, and flash photography techniques.
Lee began taking documentary photographs in Woodstock in 1935 and went to Pennsylvania to photograph bootleg coal miners. The winter of 1935 found him in New York City documenting the poor and their living conditions. Shortly after, he acquired an agent and began selling his work to magazines. In 1936, Lee joined the photographic staff of the Resettlement Administration, later renamed the Farm Security Administration (FSA), where he worked under the creative supervision of Roy Stryker, director of photographic projects. His colleagues included Dorothea Lange, Arthur Rothstein, Walker Evans, and Carl Mydans. During his FSA years, Lee traveled throughout the United States, documenting life in rural and urban communities. He developed a flash technique that enabled him to take innovative and candid interior photographs. He also specialized in taking pictures in series, most notably those shot in Pie Town, New Mexico, and San Augustine, Texas.
The long periods away from his wife while working for the FSA contributed to their divorce in 1938. On assignment in New Orleans the same year, he met Jean Smith, a Dallas journalist. They began working together and eventually married.
In 1943, Lee received a captain's commission in the Air Transport Command (ATC). He traveled military transport routes taking aerial photographs, visiting the West Indies, North Africa, India, and China. Lee was promoted to major and received the Air Medal.
About a year after leaving the ATC, in 1946, Lee was hired by the Department of the Interior's Coal Mines Administration to take photographs for a major report on health and safety conditions in bituminous coal mines.
The Lees moved to Austin, Texas, in 1947. At the request of his former FSA chief, Roy Stryker, Lee worked for Standard Oil of New Jersey, documenting the oil industry at home and overseas. Lee continued with industrial photography projects throughout the 1950's, visiting Saudi Arabia and Europe. He contributed to Fortune magazine and was an associate staff member of the prestigious Magnum photographic cooperative.
Between 1949 and 1962, Lee conducted a photographic workshop at the University of Missouri. In 1950, Lee worked with The University of Texas on a study of Spanish-speaking people in Texas. He contributed to the Texas Observer and between 1952 and 1957 covered Ralph Yarborough's election campaigns. His coverage of a 1956 Texas primary campaign appeared in The New York Times. The September, 1961, issue of Texas Quarterly published 150 of some 4,000 photographs taken during a two-and-a-half month visit to Italy.
In 1965, The University of Texas at Austin presented an exhibition of Lee's photographs and he was invited to join the university's art faculty as an instructor in photography. He taught until his retirement in 1973. Russell Lee died on August 28, 1986.
Index Terms
Subjects
Portrait photography -- United States.; Documentary photography; Photography; Photographers; World War, 1939-1945
Places
United States -- Social life and customs -- 1918-1945 -- Pictorial works
Subjects (Persons)
Lee, Russell, 1903-1986; Lee, Dorothy Jean
Subjects (Corporations)
United States. Coal Mines Administration; United States. Farm Security Administration; United States. Air Force. Air Transport Command
- Correspondence, 1918-1990; 1972-1979
  Series Description
  Arranged into subseries for correspondence to Russell Lee and to Jean Lee, this material is filed in alphabetical order by the name of the correspondent. The bulk of the correspondence to Russell Lee is comprised of letters from Jack Hurley regarding their collaboration on the book, Russell Lee: Photographer.
  - Letters to Russell Lee, 1918, 1942, 1972-1979
    - Curtis, James C. (Three letters specifically related to making arrangements for an interview.), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hurley, Jack, 1972-1979
    - 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      Contents
      Includes 2 versions of the manuscript. The first version was sent to Lee with a letter dated May 11. The second version has changes made to page 33.
    - 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lange, Dorothea, and Taylor, Paul (New Year Greeting), March 16, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - O'Neal, Hank, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - OWI Staff (caricature/farewell card from "The Gang" signed by the OWI staff, circa 1942 (Box 4)
  - Pope, Milton (Lee's uncle), December 20, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Jean Lee, 1989-1990
    - Maverick, Maury, Jr. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Museum of New Mexico (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Reid, Robert (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Southwest Texas State University (Francine Carraro) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Personal Documents, 1881, 1900-1901, 1930s-1970s
  This series contains three of Russell Lee's FSA field notebooks (late 1930s-early 1940s), with his notes which were later used to write captions for his FSA photographs. After a certain point in time, Jean Lee took over the duty of gathering this information and maintaining notebooks for this purpose. The notebooks maintained by Jean Lee are presumed to have been discarded by Ms. Lee after Russell Lee's death. Other materials in this series include family documents such as Russell Lee's mother's diary from 1900-1901, the family Bible dating from 1881, as well as some of Jean Lee's writing assignments dating from 1967.
  - Werner Family Bible, December 26, 1881 (Box 9)
  - Diary of Mrs. Burton (Adeline) Cook Lee, Lee's mother, October 10, 1900-May 29, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Russell Lee Notebooks, 1930s-1940s, 1970s
    - 3 FSA field notebooks, circa 1935-1945 (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
    - General notebook, circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 2 note cards, in Lee's hand (possibly from one of the notebooks), undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Jean Lee Writings, 1967, undated
    - Famous Writer's School (Westport, Connecticut). Assignments for: Section I, Section II, and Sections III-V, October 17, 1967, December 8, 1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Other writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Legal Documents, 1914, 1939-1991
  Documents including and relating to the will of Russell Lee's maternal grandmother, Eva Werner, comprise the first subseries of this series, and relate in part to a half-sister of Lee's. Other documents include a divorce decree for Russell Lee and his first wife, birth and marriage certificates for Russell and Jean Lee, passports for both Lees, and financial records related to a household employee.
  - Documents Relating to Eva Werner's Will, 1949, 1986, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Will, dated June 11, 1914 (copy from March 9, 1949)
    Trustee Report from March 1, 1983 to August 28, 1986
    Form Complaint (contest), October 15, 1986
    Legal correspondence to Jean Lee (October 28, 1986 to July 1, 1990)
  - Certificates, 1939, 1953, 1963-1966
    - Divorce papers, Doris Lee and Russell Lee, December 7, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Marriage certificate, Jean Smith Martin and Russell Lee, December 15, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Birth certificate, Russell Werner Lee [date of birth: July 21, 1903], April 30, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Birth certificate, Dorothy Jean Smith [date of birth: April 13, 1908], July 10, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Russell Lee's international certificate of vaccination, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Passports, 1953-1985
    - Russell Lee (6), 1953-1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Jean Lee (6), 1953-1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Financial Documents, 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Tax records relating to Naomi Lott (household employee), 1984, 1988, 1989, 1990, 1991. NOTE: Folder contains envelopes for 1985 and 1987, but these envelopes contain no records.
- President's Commission on Coal, 1978-1979, undated
  Correspondence, financial documents, and guidelines and working papers comprise this series which relates not to Russell Lee's work with the Coal Mine Administration, but to his role as consultant to the President's Commission on Coal in the late 1970s.
  - Letters sent to Russell Lee relating to his capacity as a consultant to the President's Commission on Coal (3), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Receipt from The University Co-Op in Austin; Purchase orders from the U.S. Department of Labor to Russell Lee covering consultant/speaker fee and expenses (2), May 1, 1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Guidelines and working papers, 1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    "Guidelines to Consultants" undated The President's Commission on Coal list of voting and non-voting members Document described as a working paper outlining issues the Commission will consider over the coming year, October 29, 1978
    Photocopies of newspaper clippings that discuss The President's Commission on Coal. Clippings, December 1978.
    10-page questionnaire, not completed. [Note: Date and origin unknown, but found in Lee's folder on President's Commission on Coal]
    List of Recommendations for coal-mining companies, photocopied from a book. [Note: Date and origin unknown, but found in Lee's folder on President's Commission on Coal]
  - Articles on Lee's work with CMA, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    In the Coal Mines Far Away: Russell Lee's Photographs of Mining Life" by Barry O'Connell [Note: handwritten on title page: Prospects 2 Edited by Jack Salzman Published by Burt Franklin & Co. 1976]
    "1946: Day by Day. The Sergent Family, Photographed by Russell W. Lee" [Note: handwritten on title page: Southern Exposure Vol 4, #1-2 Spring/Summer 1976]
- Exhibits and Publications, 1947-1986
  This series includes catalogs, a booklet, and a poster related to exhibits of Russell Lee's works (one exhibit by the Coal Mine Administration in 1947, one by the University of Texas at Austin in 1965, and one by Texas A&M in 1986). Articles related Lee's work in general complete this series
  - Booklet entitled "The Coal Miner and His Family: A Supplement to A Medical Survey of the Bituminous-Coal Industry" published by Department of the Interior, Washington, Contains many photographs by Russell Lee when employed by the Coal Mines Administration, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letter by Jim Hightower serving as exhibit text celebrating Russell Lee's political campaign photographs of Ralph Yarborough, unidentified exhibit location/date. Booklet featuring Lee's photos of Yarborough, 1954-1957 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Two 16-page illustrated catalogs for the Retrospective Exhibition held at the University of Texas Art Museum [Note: A piece of typing paper with an update of Lee's career written in the mid-1970s has been taped to page 3 of one of the catalogs], February 28 - March 29, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Image [Vol. 16, No. 3] issue. Publication of International Museum of Photography at George Eastman House. Entire issue is devoted to article on Russell Lee written by Jack Hurley, September 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Poster for exhibit entitled "A Russell Lee Portfolio: early Texas portraits" held at Texas A&M, September 1-October 8, 1986 (Box 4)
- Interview, 1964
  This series is comprised of one transcript with corrections and edits from an interview of Russell Lee by Richard Doud, on June 2, 1964.
  - Annotated transcript from interview with Richard Doud, June 2, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Clippings, 1945-1992
  The clippings in this series relate to Russell Lee's photographic career, and appear to have been maintained by both Russell and Jean Lee. Clippings regarding Lee's death were maintained by Jean Lee.
  - 1945-1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1986 - Tributes (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1987-1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Awards and Artifacts, 1919-1986
  This seriesincludes some of the awards given to Russell Lee throughout his career, arranged in chronological order, beginning with one from his high school, Culver Military Academy, dating from 1919-1920. Lee's World War II Air Medal and other WWII decorations, as well a Resolution commemorating Lee's efforts on behalf of the Coal Mine Administration (1947) are also included in this series. A Texas State Senate Resolution presented to Jean Lee in 1986 in memory of Russell Lee is also present. Also included are the following artifacts: Air Transport Command cap, Lee's camera bag for the ATC, and the Werner family bible.
  - Senate resolution in memory of Russell Lee presented to Jean Lee, September 4, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Resolution from Coal Mines Administration to Russell Lee, June 30, 1947 (Box 4)
  - Leather Air Medal box with Air Medal: "Major Russell W. Lee A.C." Box also contains a variety of World War II decorations (Box 5)
  - Silver cup [from Culver Military Academy]: Presented by "D" Co. to Cadet Russell W. Lee who has shown the most company spirit and done the most for the company during the school year, 1919-1920 (Box 6)
  - [Copper] Award: Presented to Russell and Jean Lee, Workshop Directors by the School of Journalism, University of Missouri. In recognition of their great contribution to photojournalism, May 17, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Air Transport Command cap (Box 8)
  - Air Transport Command Camera Bag (Box 10)
- Photographs of Russell and Jean Lee, 1904-1984
  The collection contains 77 photographs of Russell Lee, the largest group known to exist. This group of photographs range from portraits by unknown studio photographers, to well known photographers such as Ave Bonar. Russell Lee is portrayed both in snapshots by anonymous photographers and candid photographs by military photographers in the Air Transport Command.
  - [Studio portrait Russell Lee as a child], circa 1904-1905 (Box 11, Item WG001)
  - [Studio portrait of Russell Lee as a child (with dog)], circa 1905 (Box 11, Item WG002)
  - [Studio portrait of Russell Lee as a child], circa 1906-1908 (Box 11, Item WG003)
  - [Studio portrait of Russell Lee as a child, dressed in a sailor outfit, and with some hand coloring], circa 1905-1908 (Box 11, Item WG004)
  - [Postcard portrait of Russell Lee sitting on a log fence, out of doors, dressed in a sailor outfit], circa 1907-1910 (Box 11, Item WG005)
  - [Postcard portrait of Russell Lee sitting on a log fence, out of doors, dressed in a sailor outfit], circa 1907-1910 (Box 11, Item WG006)
  - [Studio portrait, postcard format, Russell Lee and his grandfather], circa 1910-1914 (Box 11, Item WG007)
  - [Studio portrait of Russell W. Lee seated in a chair, arms crossed. Signed and dated in pencil by studio] Ottowa, IL, 1913 (Box 11, Item WG008)
  - [Studio portrait of Russell W. Lee seated in a chair, arms crossed. Signed and dated in pencil by studio] Ottowa, IL, 1913 (Box 11, Item WG009)
  - [Studio portrait of Russell Lee in Culver Academy uniform. Signed by the studio. Inscription on photo: "With love to grandpa and Mert From Russell"], 1921 (Box 11, Item WG010)
  - [Studio portrait of Russell Lee in Culver Academy uniform. Inscription on photo: "With love to Father from Russell 1921"] (Box 11, Item WG011)
  - [Unidentified tintype of two children. (Included with Russell Lee family photographs donated by Jean Lee.)], undated (Box 11, Item WG012)
  - Russell Lee, Woodstock, New York, 1936 (Box 11, Item WG013)
  - [Russell Lee and friends at a social gathering.], circa 1935-1945 (Box 11, Item WG014)
  - [Russell Lee and friends at a social gathering.], circa 1935-1945 (Box 11, Item WG015)
  - [Studio portrait of Russell Lee (looking off-camera)], circa 1935-1945 (Box 11, Item WG016)
  - [Studio portrait of Russell Lee (smiling)], circa 1935-1945 (Box 11, Item WG017)
  - [Studio portrait of Russell Lee], circa 1935-1945 (Box 11, Item WG017a)
  - [Russell Lee seated outside on a lawn chair], circa 1935-1945 (Box 11, Item WG018)
  - [Russell Lee seated outside on a lawn chair], circa 1935-1945 (Box 11, Item WG019)
  - Captain Russell W. Lee, Chief of Still Picture Section, Overseas Technical Unit, Air Transport Command at Roberts Field. Liberia, Africa, 1943 (Box 11, Item WG020)
  - Captain Russell W. Lee, Chief of Still Picture Section, Overseas Technical Unit, Air Transport Command at Roberts Field. Liberia, Africa, 1943 (Box 11, Item WG020a)
  - Captain Russell W. Lee, Chief of Still Picture Section, Overseas Technical Unit, Air Transport Command at Roberts Field. Liberia, Africa, 1943 (Box 11, Item WG020b)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee (in Air Transport Command uniform) seated on loveseat with Clara Dean Wickham (FSA secretary). Roy Stryker is kneeling behind loveseat.], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG021)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee (in ATC uniform) holding and looking at jacket], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG022)
  - [Russell W. Lee holding camera and lens, looking up at photographer. Photograph probably taken when employed by Air Transport Command], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG023)
  - [Major Russell W. Lee in the Air Transport Command looking over the shoulder of unidentified Sergeant], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG024)
  - [Unidentified man tying civilian tie on Major Russell W. Lee in the Air Transport Command], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG025)
  - [Major Russell W. Lee in the Air Transport Command (standing with hand on hip, looking off-camera)], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG026)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee in the Air Transport Command (far right) seated with fellow military personnel], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG027)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee in the Air Transport Command seated with other military personnel], undated (Box 11, Item WG027a)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee in the Air Transport Command (middle) seated with fellow military personnel], undated (Box 11, Item WG027b)
  - [Russell W. Lee (with camera in hand)] [Photograph is mounted on larger, annotated board], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG028)
  - [Major Russell Lee receiving Air Medal as unidentified Sergeant First Class looks on], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG029)
  - [Major Russell Lee receiving Air Medal as unidentified Sergeant First Class looks on], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG029a)
  - [Unidentified Sergeant First Class receiving Air Medal as Major Russell Lee looks on.], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG030)
  - [Major Russell W. Lee and unidentified Sergeant First Class upon receiving their Air Medals], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG031)
  - [Russell Lee drinking out of well], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG032)
  - [Russell Lee drinking out of well], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG032a)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee resting on airplane], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG033)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee resting on airplane], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG033a)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee resting on airplane], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG034)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee resting on airplane], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG035)
  - [Air Transport Command crew (Russell Lee is fourth from the left) in] Morocco, circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG036)
  - [Air Transport Command crew (Russell Lee is fourth from the left) in] Morocco, circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG037)
  - [Air Transport Command crew (Russell Lee is fourth from the left) in] Morocco, circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG038)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG039)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG040)
  - Captain Russell W. Lee leaning out of door of ATC plane with camera in hand], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG041)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee looking through viewfinder in airplane], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG041a)
  - [Captain Russell W. Lee leaning out of door of ATC plane with camera in hand], circa 1942-1945 (Box 11, Item WG042)